I do have a word from the Lord [music]
today.
Praise the Lord.
I want to share with you today and pick
right up [music] from
where we left off last week standing at
the Red Sea.
And Pharaoh and his chariots are behind
us and
>> [music]
>> an impossible looking obstacle is in
front of us.
And last week I preached a message
called it still works.
When I said that I was referring to the
rod, the stick, the staff that Moses
held in his hand.
And I was sharing just as we closed and
we ran out of time how
he had seen that the stick could turn
into a snake when he threw it on the
ground.
But he was about to find out that it'll
work in water, too.
And my message to you was don't be
afraid when you face a new challenge.
Because what God gave you back then is
good enough to get you through this,
too.
And I do want to encourage somebody
today, you'll get through this, too.
You've been through a lot of things and
you'll get through [music] this, too.
But I I want to get much more specific
today.
So, I'm going to share from Exodus
chapter 14, verses 10
through 16.
And then one more verse as well.
And I'll give you the title in just a
moment, but read with me here.
The people of God are looking forward to
a brand new beginning. God has sent them
a deliverer named Moses. He has
unleashed 10 plagues on Pharaoh
and the Egyptian households.
God's people are no sooner out of Egypt
>> [music]
>> than Egypt starts trying to get back
into them.
I have found out that
it's one thing for you to let Pharaoh
go. It's another thing for Pharaoh to
let you go.
And sometimes Pharaoh lets you go and
you still don't let him go.
>> [music]
>> And sometimes God sets you free from
something, but it has an effect in your
life and
you thinking, "Man, I thought I was
starting over. I thought this was a
fresh beginning for me." And just as
they
are moving forward into their fresh
beginning as the people of God
and [music] staring at the Red Sea, they
hear a familiar sound of the chariots
of the armies of Pharaoh. Now, watch
their response in verse 10.
As Pharaoh approached, the Israelites
looked up and there were the Egyptians
marching after them.
They were terrified and cried out to the
Lord.
They said to Moses,
"Was it because there were no graves in
Egypt that you brought us to the desert
to die?
What have you done to us
by bringing us out of Egypt?
Didn't we say to you in Egypt, 'Leave us
alone.
Let us serve the Egyptians.'
It would have been better for us to
serve the Egyptians than to die in the
desert." [music]
Moses answered the people, "Do not be
afraid.
Stand firm.
And you will see the deliverance the
Lord will bring you today.
The Egyptians you see today, you will
never see again. The Lord will fight for
you. You need only to be still."
Now, that verse, verse 14, is
complicated
because half of it is correct and half
of it is misleading.
The Lord will fight for you.
But that second part, you need only to
be still,
the Lord speaks up and corrects it in
verse 15.
>> [music]
>> Now, listen to this verse because this
is the hinge for my message. Then the
Lord said to Moses,
"Why are you crying out to me?
Tell the Israelites
to move on.
Raise your staff."
Touch your neighbor, say, "It still
works."
It still works. Raise your staff, the
same staff that worked with the sheep,
the same staff that turned into a snake,
the same staff that turned the Nile into
blood, the same staff that called down
hail from heaven. That same staff, raise
it now and stretch out your hand over
the sea to divide the water.
So that the Israelites can go through
the sea on dry ground. Now, drop down
please to verse 21 and 22. Then Moses
stretched out his hand over the sea and
all that night the Lord drove back the
sea with a strong east wind and turned
it into dry land. The waters were
divided and the Israelites went through
the sea on dry ground with the wall of
water on their right
and on their left.
What a story. One more verse. Romans
chapter 8 verse 31.
You're going [music] to like this one.
You're going to be tempted to get a
tattoo of this one.
Ask your parents first though.
You might want to set your alarm to 8:31
a.m. tomorrow morning so you can
remember this one when the alarm goes
off.
See what you think about this verse.
What then
shall we say
in response to these things?
If God is for us
who
can be
against us?
>> [music]
>> I don't know where you're at in this
story. I don't know what chapter you're
stuck in.
>> [music]
>> But the title of my message is you can
change the end.
You can change the end.
>> [music]
>> I don't know how much time you've
wasted, but you can change the end.
I don't know if you like what it looks
like today, but you can change the end.
I don't know if you've been a good
Christian in high school, but you can
change the end.
You can change the end.
Father, give us faith to receive the
impartation of your word in Jesus' name.
>> [music]
>> Amen. Touch three people, say change it
on your way to your seat.
Cuz you can change the end.
You can change the end.
Boy, what a thought. You can change the
end.
You can change the end.
See, because a fresh start is
technically impossible.
I know we all want one. I know we may
need one, but
you know the experiences of your past
don't evaporate as you move into your
future. And you know that.
You know that. It doesn't keep us from
praying. God, just give me like
a reset. Like like if it was a video
game. I just just go back and do that
again.
You can't really have a fresh start. But
what I want to try to show you today
practically is
that you can't get a fresh start, but
you can take a forward step.
So,
we have three responses essentially in
this passage that I just read you
to an impossible obstacle.
And I'll break them down for you as we
begin. The first response is the
response of God's people.
The response of God's people.
And their response to be summed up in
two words is it's [snorts] over, right?
We've only been free
for [clears throat] a few days
and here comes Pharaoh to drag us back
and it's over.
That's their response.
And not only are they responding it's
over with desperation,
but their desperation leads to anger
with Moses.
Um specifically because they are afraid,
they get angry.
And so, the anger is a response to the
fear.
Because rather than just feel the fear
and move forward,
they stop in a place to place blame on
the person whose fault they think it is.
So, anytime that you see someone who is
angry, including yourself, ask the
question, "What are they afraid of?"
Because the anger is usually a
masquerade for the fact that they're
afraid.
That's the response of God's people.
It's over, and they're afraid, and they
start doing revisionist history. Moses,
we told you to leave us alone. No, you
didn't. You begged him to bring you out.
We told you we were better off in Egypt.
No, you didn't tell us you better off in
Egypt. You're adding that part back. I
found out that oftentimes
our version of the past is just as
imaginary as our version of the future.
And we go back through things,
especially when we're feeling paralyzed,
and we project things onto the past that
never happened. So, that's the situation
with God's people. Everybody say, "It's
over."
Put it in the chat. It's over. That's
their response. Response number two is
Moses.
And Moses is trying to bring some calm.
He's like, "Breathing everybody, box
breathing everybody, four in, hold it
four, four out, downward dog, upward
dog, whatever y'all need to do to chill
out. Be still.
God's got this."
And he's saying the thing that it would
be appropriate for a leader to say in
this situation. His response is, "Stand
still."
But there's a third response in the
passage that we want to talk about for a
few moments today, and I want to apply
directly to your life and the situations
that you're facing that seem impossible,
and the past is threatening to drag drag
you back, and it looks like it's over.
God's response says, "Move on."
So, there are three responses for us to
consider here today. One is desperation
followed by fear,
and then manifesting in anger, it's
over. The second one is the response of
Moses, where he says, "Stand still.
God's going to do it. It's going to be
fine."
And then the third one is God's
response. And um
spoiler alert, God's right, and Moses is
wrong. Now,
I wish I could teach a leadership
session off of this text because
I would really love to. One of my
favorite things to teach as a leader,
for those who work closely with me
especially, I always train this. I say,
"Big doors swing on little hinges."
I didn't make that up, but I say it all
the time. And I'm trying to get them to
understand when I say that to them is,
"You may think this really doesn't
matter,
but big doors
swing on little hinges."
You know, it it matters to me how we run
our e-kids ministry. Do you know what
I'm saying? Because if they feed your
kid a, you know, a rotten animal cracker
and they get sick in the emergency room
or something like that and you sue the
church, you know, or if they choke back
there, that could be a big a big door to
a lawsuit that swings on a little hinge.
So, I'm like, "Let's be safe in the
children's ministry." Or even even
little things. I mess up things
sometimes
and I have to tell myself, you know,
slow down
because big doors
swing on little hinges.
In the case of Moses, you might ask the
question when God gives him the command
to stretch out his staff over the sea,
>> [clears throat]
>> "What good is something so small
stretched over something so big? How
could something as small as a stick
affect something as big as a sea?" Well,
big doors
swing on little hinges.
Or you might say, "Big seas open with
little sticks."
And that would be a good leadership
sermon.
Even just the other week, I didn't tell
you this yet, LJ, but I messed up. I
texted Tiffany that I wanted her to do
her new song
and I wanted her and David to sing it.
And when I sent the text, I said, "We
need to try it in church one Sunday."
This was on a Saturday night and I
wasn't going to be at church the next
day. I was off that weekend.
And so, I texted her. I said, "Hey, we
need to do that in church. We haven't
done it in church yet. We need to do it
in church one Sunday.
Well, I turned on church online and they
were doing it the next day.
I thought, "Wow, what a turnaround time.
What an inspiring motivational leader I
am."
They did it that quick. I mean, I
thought maybe they would get everybody
ready and let the band rehearse. They
turned that thing around quick.
And I thought, "Well, that's kind of
strange, you know, they should have
given the band more time to learn it and
maybe the singers and everything like
that."
So, I pulled back up the text and I
said, "Man, why was Tiffany so
overzealous? Like, we didn't have to do
it within 12 hours. We could have done
it next week or something like that."
And I pulled back up the text that said,
"We need to do it
one Sunday." Or so I thought I texted,
but what I actually texted was on
Sunday.
So, big inconvenience
for them
because of one letter for me.
And now everybody's scrambling to learn
a song and I didn't mean we have to do
it tomorrow, but but one letter.
Everybody say one letter. One word. One
word. Just one word. And now is having
to pull out chord charts because you
have to understand that big doors
swing on little hinges.
Good marriages die by little eye rolls.
Big problems, big addictions
begin with little curiosities.
By the same token, great joy can erupt
from small praise.
Yeah.
And by the same token, just just a small
decision, the smallest decision that you
make
can be a hinge to the biggest event. And
I'll prove it to you from this, the
Exodus narrative. Exodus means exit.
This is to be the defining
distinguishing miracle of the people of
God for centuries to come and it starts
with a stick because big doors swing on
little hinges. But it matters in this
moment for Moses
what response will you give
when the results are not under your
control?
>> [snorts]
>> And this is the separation that we have
to make for the decisions of our life,
too.
When God corrects Moses in this passage
because the people are crying out and
asking him to do something about their
enemy,
and he says that
what you have in your hand is enough for
what I've called you to do next.
Remember, something as small as a stick,
little hinges, something as big as a
sea, big door. What is that picture for
you today? I need you to stop and think
about it so that we don't dislocate our
application by going back into the past
of the history of the text and realizing
that you yourself are standing at hinge
moments every day. That's what I call
them, hinge moments.
It's the moment where you decide go
back, go forward, stand still.
It It's the moment where you decide
continue to blame and become more and
more bitter
or forgive and be set free for my
future. It's a hinge moment. And you
say, "Well, it's not that big of a
deal." It is a big deal
because the smallest of offenses can
become
the most unforgiving prisons.
And it matters what you do in this
moment. Now,
Moses
and the children of Israel have a
perspective
on this miracle
that we do not have because they had to
respond
in real time.
And this is the challenge not that we
would
respond to God's goodness with praise on
Sunday.
My goal for you when you leave this
sermon today and every Sunday
is that your real-time response would
reflect what God spoke to you in the
service.
So, that means that
when you get bumped by life, the word
that you receive from God comes out of
you instead of the other stuff.
Cuz there is some other stuff that comes
out of us.
I got an encouraging testimony from
Lindsey who serves on our staff. Y'all
Y'all give Lindsey a hand real quick.
And she said,
>> [applause]
>> "Thank you for the message that you
preached last week." She said, "It
really helped me." She said, "You talked
about how sometimes you have to do it
doubting, and the Lord really confirmed
something for me." I said, "Well, what
was it if you don't mind me asking?" She
said, "I have been feeling overwhelmed
by the responsibilities that my boss,
who is Chad, and he's also here today,
has been asking me to fulfill." Now, she
was texting me this, all right? She was
saying, "I've been feeling overwhelmed
because he's been asking me to step up,
and I have been shrinking back."
Because not only does she have a very
young and growing family, but she said,
"I was comparing myself to the other
leaders and how they did it. I was
comparing myself to people that I think
are more confident, but the Lord really
spoke to me that I need to step up in my
area of responsibility." And he used the
word that you preached to confirm that.
Now, she was thanking me for the word,
and then I started thanking her for her
thank you. And I'll tell you why.
I said, "Lindsey, thank you so much for
this text. It's so refreshing.
Do you know how many times I've preached
sermons and people have used them as an
excuse not to step up in responsibility,
but to bail out on their responsibility?
I remember one time there was somebody
who told me I was preaching about when
the Israelites left Egypt, and I was
preaching specifically how they had to
leave before the yeast had a chance to
rise. And they were listening to me
preach, and what they took from that
message was, 'God is calling me to quit
my job. I don't have another one lined
up. I don't have health insurance and I
have kids. My husband doesn't have a
job. We don't have another thing to step
into. But Pastor, when you said leave
Egypt before the bread has time to rise,
I just decided to quit. And the
organization they were quitting was
Elevation Church. So now I'm thinking,
am I Pharaoh in this analogy? Like if
you're going to play the whole thing
out,
cuz last time I checked you were getting
a check.
So this is not exactly a situation for
for you to escape.
And I texted Lindsey back something and
the Lord told me to put it in my sermon
for you today. Beware of any word from
God that pulls you toward an escape from
reality rather than an embrace of
responsibility.
>> [applause]
>> SHALL I SAY IT AGAIN?
I want you to get this. Beware of any
word from God, cuz we think we get a
word from God. Well, beware of any
interpretation of a word from God that
pulls you toward an escape from reality
rather than an embrace from
responsibility.
Because sometimes we confuse freedom
with relief.
Sometimes we will believe that God is
saying something to us because it is
what we have already decided we wanted
to hear. Sometimes it is not the word of
God, it is confirmation bias that makes
us think that we heard the Lord say
something. But the Lord did not tell you
to leave somebody that you committed
your life to. The Lord did not tell you
to just hop around from church to church
every time you get offended by one
person. The Lord wants you to stay long
enough to learn how to work through an
offense in the place where you are, so
you don't end up in the prison of always
having to run from place to place.
>> [applause]
>> So
>> it is a good way to discern a word from
God. Am I just trying to get out of
something or am I going towards
something? And if you don't even know
what you're going toward, it may not be
God's word, it may just be your wish.
And who among us doesn't want to escape
a situation? But I have found that in
many cases by trying to escape a
situation, you end up in a worse prison
than you were in to begin with because
now you have imprisoned yourself to the
flippant decision that you made to walk
away from something that God was calling
you to step up in.
>> [applause]
>> Wow.
>> So, I said, "Thank you, Lindsey. That
means a lot to me."
Cuz it's rare that somebody will take
God's word as a challenge to step up.
We're always looking for God's word to
get us out of stuff. I'll give you
another example.
I really want to break this down cuz
you're like, "He's just fussing cuz
people leave the church." No.
I mean, you can leave if God tells you
to leave. I'm just trying to get you not
to leave things that God has called you
to be loyal to.
There's a reason we love the Red Sea
miracle. It's because they're getting
out.
And we love that kind of story. We're
getting out. Did you miss the fact they
had to go through?
And even when they got through, guess
where they landed? The wilderness.
Now you got to go through that.
So, here's an example.
I've heard so many sermons and preached
many myself about how when people leave
your life, it's just God getting you
ready for the next level.
And you know that uh chickens can't fly
with eagles. So, tell them goodbye and
go to the next level. But I want to ask
you a question.
If every 3 weeks
you need a message about everybody
leaving your life,
is there a leak in your life that is
causing everybody to leave.
Mhm. Because if all we give you is an
encouragement that God has somebody
better and better and better, you will
look beyond the people that God put in
front of you for the better one that
they tell you is coming. But even if God
sends the better one, if you don't get
better at relationships, they'll leave,
too.
Now you're leaking the next relationship
cuz I'm going to the next level. You're
not going to the next level, you are
leaking love.
So it's important that you get this
message so that you get the right
response. In real time. In real time. So
that you can come
to what looks like the end
and there can come seasons in your life
where you think like, it's totally over.
I've totally blown it. This is it. I
will never be happy again. I will never
have joy again. My best is behind me.
Have you've ever thought any of those
thoughts in your life, wave at me so I
don't stand up here in my purple shirt
looking like Barney the dinosaur all by
myself. Wave at me. Wave at me. Wave at
me. Wave at me.
Here Here's the phrase. Put it on the
board, please.
The end.
Okay, so let's act it out. Children of
Israel, Bible says they went out of
Egypt marching boldly.
I love that part. They were marching
boldly until they heard something behind
them. You know how you get all cocky
while you're in church. Tell the devil,
you messed with the wrong one. But at
6:00 p.m. tonight, God, why is the devil
picking on me? You know, now you go from
from bring it to God, please get me out
of this. God, I'm sorry. I'll never do
it again, Lord. And so as they're
leaving and and they're they're moving
toward a fresh start, remember? And then
they hear a familiar sound and they come
to the end of the road.
The end.
We're going to die here.
It's over.
This is the end.
This is it.
And it looked like that. And it feels
like that. Can I be honest? There have
been so many times in my ministry where
I have thought my effectiveness and my
relevance has seen its greatest season
and now I'm going down. There were times
where people criticized me publicly and
I thought I'll never recover from this.
There have been times where I lost my
own joy and I thought I don't know how
I'm going to get it back to preach. I've
been in seasons like this before and it
feels like
the end.
And [clears throat] Moses' response is
very tempting here. Just be still. The
people ARE LIKE, "IT'S OVER."
THE END. [screaming]
PUT IT ON THE SCREEN, Y'ALL.
THE WHITE SCREEN. It's the end.
And and and Moses is like, "JUST BE
STILL."
AND GOD'S LIKE, "YOU'RE GOING TO DIE."
RIGHT?
GRAHAM SAID LAST WEEK, "EVERY Steven
Furtick sermon ends the same way. You're
going to make it."
So I thought I'd change it up this week.
YOU MIGHT NOT.
YOU LIKE THAT?
You can't say that no more now, CAN YOU?
YOU MIGHT NOT MAKE IT.
AND
NOT IF YOU DON'T RESPOND RIGHT IN THIS
MOMENT.
I'M NOT SAYING YOU'RE AUTOMATICALLY
GOING TO HAVE A BETTER TOMORROW JUST CUZ
GOD IS WITH YOU TODAY. SO FOR THE FIRST
TIME EVER AT ELEVATION CHURCH, TOUCH
YOUR NEIGHBOR AND SAY, "YOU MIGHT NOT
MAKE IT."
YOU MIGHT NOT MAKE IT. STEVEN FURTICK
TOLD YOU THAT. IT'S ON A STEVEN FURTICK
PODCAST. YOU MIGHT NOT MAKE IT. IF THEY
DID WHAT MOSES SAID, THEY WOULD HAVE
DIED CUZ YOU'VE GOT TO
>> [screaming]
>> MOVE ON.
>> [applause]
>> YOU MIGHT NOT MAKE IT IF YOU KEEP
LISTENING TO ALL THE SAD SONGS AND NEVER
LISTEN TO A HAPPY ONE. YOU MIGHT NOT
MAKE IT BACK NEXT SUNDAY IF YOU KEEP
FEEDING YOURSELF ALL THE STUFF YOU'VE
BEEN feeding yourself.
So, I thought I would uplift the people
of God and edify the saints by telling
you the message you might not make it.
It all depends on your response.
Because when you are standing at the
end, watch this, the end of the dream,
the end of the vision, the end of the
relationship, the end, the end, the end.
There's There's There's so many
unmentionable situations in this room
today that are so deeply painful that if
I said them right now, IT WOULD TAKE YOU
OUT OF THE REST OF THE SERMON CUZ YOU'D
GO, "THAT'S ME. THAT'S WHERE I'M
STANDING. I AM PARALYZED. I'M LIKE the
people. I'm angry cuz I WAS AFRAID. I'M
AFRAID BECAUSE I'M DESPERATE BECAUSE IT
LOOKS LIKE THE END, which is why verse
15 of Exodus 14 is the hinge of this
entire lesson that God has given us,
where the Bible says, "Then the Lord
said to Moses." Then the Lord said to
Moses. Then the Lord said to Moses that
what you need for this next season is in
the feet of the people moving forward
into what looks like an impossible
situation. Then the Lord said to Moses.
So, my announcement today is if you are
standing at the end of something,
standing looking at something that looks
impossible FOR YOU TO NAVIGATE, AND YOU
DON'T KNOW HOW, THE LORD SAID TO TELL
YOU you can change the end. Change it,
Jared. You can change
the end.
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> Oh.
Come on, y'all got to do better than
that. I worked on that. I worked like a
dog to show you that.
>> [applause]
>> Go back and do it again. They missed it.
They missed it.
I'mma to you another chance. I'm going
to give you another chance. I know you
woke up late. I know you put on those
shoes that are half size too small. I
know you you throat hurts a little bit.
You got that pollen thing going on. It
haven't been raining enough in
Charlotte. I know you just weren't ready
for it. BUT THE LORD SAID, "I KNOW IT
LOOKS BAD. I KNOW IT LOOKS DIRE. I KNOW
YOU FEEL DESPERATE. I KNOW YOU'RE KIND
OF ANGRY. I KNOW THEY LET YOU DOWN. I
KNOW THEY WALKED AWAY. I KNOW IT'S BEEN
A ROUGH NIGHT. I KNOW IT'S BEEN A ROUGH
YEAR. I KNOW IT'S BEEN A ROUGH SEASON. I
KNOW THEY ABUSED YOU. I KNOW THEY LEFT
YOU. I KNOW THEY ABANDONED YOU. BUT WHAT
I PUT IN YOUR HAND, WHEN MY WORD COMES,
CHANGE IT, JARED. YOU CAN CHANGE THE
END."
CUZ THEN
THE LORD
said [music] to Moses,
"Move.
Move."
Slap your neighbor [music] say, "Move."
I'll give you a little push start.
I'll give you a little jump start. Move.
>> [music]
>> MOVE.
COME ON. SLAP FIVE PEOPLE SO HARD THEY
GET SCARED AND SAY, "MOVE."
>> [music]
>> CUZ YOU MIGHT NOT MAKE IT IF YOU DON'T
MOVE.
BUT IF YOU WILL TAKE WHAT'S IN YOUR
HAND, [music]
I SAID if you will take what's in your
hand,
it's good enough
to get you through this, [music] too.
Somebody take a step say, "Move."
>> [music]
>> Take a step and move. Take a step and
move. Take a step and trust [music] God.
TAKE A STEP AND PRAY ABOUT IT. Take a
step and praise him again. Take a step
and raise that baby. [music]
Take a step and go back TO THE DOCTOR
AND SAY, "I'M GOING TO DO THE TREATMENT,
but I trust God. Move."
Move.
>> [music]
>> Move.
The people say, "Why?" Moses says stand.
God said move.
And you've got to learn how to respond
in real time.
You might need to put this this message
that I preached that one part as your
alarm at 8:31 tomorrow morning.
Cuz remember Romans 8:31. I don't know
if y'all forgot it already.
It's pretty powerful cuz the the the
Romans 8:31 kind of is my whole message.
Put it on the screen, please. What then
Justin help us teach today. Circle the
word then. What then
shall we say
in response to these things? What
things? He goes on to name them. Danger,
pestilence, nakedness, famine, sword,
trouble, anything you can name. Paul
says, what then shall we say in response
to these things? What what what then?
Then. Show them again. It looks like the
end. It looks like it's over, but what
Change it. Then
shall we say in response
to these things? That's my question to
you today. What then do you need to say
in response
to these things?
Because if you don't get to then, you
don't make it. You might not make it if
you don't get to then. So, it looks like
this. My dad pulled me aside when I was
a young boy. He said, "Son, alcoholism
runs in our family. It is a genetic
disposition for you to be an alcoholic.
My father was an alcoholic. I struggle
with alcoholism. As far back as I can
see, there were alcoholics on the Ferdic
side of the family tree. But son, YOU
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO DO this
different."
So, what he's saying is EVEN THOUGH I
MADE SOME MISTAKES, YOU DON'T HAVE TO
MAKE THE SAME [music] MISTAKES THAT I
made if you get to live WHAT THEN?
>> [music]
>> WHAT THEN?
LOOK AT YOUR NEIGHBOR AND ASK THEM NICE.
SAY, "WHAT THEN?"
WHAT THEN? THAT'S WHAT THE CHILDREN OF
ISRAEL ISRAEL have to decide in the
moment. I know you don't like the
chariots chasing you. I know it wasn't
fair how your story got started, but you
can change the end. You can change the
end. What then? There you go, Jared.
Change it. Change it. Change it. What
then needs to come next in your life cuz
there are no fresh starts, but there are
forward steps. What then? What then?
What then? What then? And you know
that's the only thing you got to figure
out in this season of your life is where
to put your foot next. What then? Not 3
years from now, 3 minutes from now. What
then?
Not 3 minutes from now, 3 seconds from
now. What then?
I see people getting tattoos all over
this church that just say, "What then?"
See, because you are a story that is
still unfolding. You are a masterpiece
in the making. There is something that
God is doing in your life that your eyes
have not seen and your ears have not
HEARD AND IT HAS NOT ENTERED INTO YOUR
HEART THE THINGS THAT GOD HAS PLANNED
FOR THEM that love him. What then shall
we say in response to these things
because one day your story will be told.
What then do you want to be in the story
when you tell it because it doesn't have
to end like it is right now. It doesn't
have to end like it is right now. It
doesn't have to end like it is right. It
doesn't HAVE TO END LIKE IT
IT DOESN'T HAVE TO END LIKE IT
You can change the end.
You can't fix the beginning.
You don't have to. JESUS DIED FOR THAT.
AH! JESUS DIED FOR THAT!
EVERYTHING YOU EVER DID.
>> [music]
>> HE TOOK NAILS IN HIS HAND SO YOU WOULD
NEVER HAVE TO PAY FOR YOUR SIN.
YEAH.
YEAH, but now we are in a moment in your
life. Give me my camera. Where it's not
what's in his hand, it's what's in yours
that's going to make the difference.
What then?
>> [applause]
>> What then?
So you may be talking to somebody about
this thing you're going through. What
then shall we say in response to these
things?
Yeah, these things.
Going through some things right now.
Don't look like chariots.
Sometimes it looks like a child custody
battle. Sometimes it looks like a child
in your home that's struggling.
Sometimes it looks like in your own
heart, you don't even want to be around
anymore. What What then is the question
shall we say
in response to these things? So maybe we
want to think about when you're telling
the story one day.
What then shall you say?
In response
to these things. The children of Israel
say it's over.
Moses says stand still. God says give it
to me again, Jared.
It's not the end
then.
Then.
When the story was told, watch this.
Exodus chapter 14 verse 21.
The real hinge
isn't what the Lord said, it's what
Moses did. Then Moses
stretched out
his hand
over the sea.
And all that night the Lord drove back
the sea with the strong east wind. Lord,
I want a strong east wind. Drive it
back. Drive back the debt. Drive back
the bankruptcy. Drive back the
depression. Drive it back. And God said,
"What will you do
>> [applause]
>> while you're waiting for me to drive
it?"
Cuz God only drove it when Moses did it.
What then?
What then? [applause and cheering]
Oh, this is going so good. Thank you,
Lord, for this word. What then? That's
what you got to answer. What then? Not
what them. It don't matter about them.
It matters about you. What then? What
then? What now? What me?
Change me. Holly made a whole Bible
study called Mrs. Better Half for
married couples who are just married,
and the entire premise is when I change
me, I change we.
What then?
Not what them? I can't You think she can
fix me?
You think she can fix this?
THIS IS UNFIXABLE. But she can love me.
She can accept me. She can be my
partner. She What then? That's what
you're always deciding in a
relationship. Oh, they cussed me out.
What then?
How do you want the story to go? Um when
the boys were real little, we went to
see this Christian movie one day, and
I'm telling you it's a Christian movie
cuz it makes the story even that much
more embarrassing for me. And I'mma put
myself out there in hopes that it might
help you to find your own story as well
because your story's not over. Your
story is not over. Your story is not
over. There is a next chapter for your
life.
There is a next chapter for your life.
But but the the way it goes, the story
you tells depends on the then that you
live right now.
So, that's what you understand. You're
living it in real time.
You're not just reading about it at the
Red Sea. You're living it in real time.
Like when I
was pulling out of that movie, the boys
were real little, too.
I reckon [snorts] Graham was eight,
Elijah was 11.
But I never forget that movie was so
boring.
So, I was already in a bad mood cuz it
was boring movie. And why do the
Christian movies have to be boring so
often? You know what I'm saying? So, I'm
like mad at us as the kingdom people of
God that we can't make a better movie.
I'm backing out the parking space.
And the um
the man honked at me.
Cuz I was backing out too slow.
And he goes, "Hey, buddy, we need your
spot.
You need my spot?
Well,
I rolled down my automatic window.
That's what I did then. So, he yells,
then I rolled down my window. Now, I
didn't roll down my window before he
yelled. That's what I did in response as
a consequence for his action to set a
good example for my boys that nobody
gets to honk at you in a pickup truck
without you rolling down the window of
your Maxima and letting them know it's
not the size of the Maxima, it's the
size of the crazy inside of me and we
can get it on right outside I don't even
care if it's the Valentine church
parking lot and I just preached the
Christian movie didn't save me that
good.
I said, "What?"
That's what I said.
And I could have said some other
four-letter words. Y'all ought to be
glad it was what.
There were some other four-letter
options circulating at that point in
time.
I said, "What?"
And then he said another four-letter
word back to me. Now, I'm out the car.
Now, at this point
I know, officer, this is bad. You almost
got called to the movie theater this
day, officer.
I said I said,
"WHAT ARE WE GOING TO DO?"
RIGHT? CUZ I really didn't know either.
But we're going back and forth and I'm
like trying to intimidate him cuz I
really don't want to fight him and I'm
trying to intimidate him. And I'm not
playing any of this out in my head too
much. I'm just doing it in real It's a
red sea of of sorts. Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> A little bit of a downgrade for the
miracle. But but I'm I'm back and forth
with this guy and all of a sudden I see
Graham
right beside me. He has now gotten out
of the car and joined his father in this
foolishness in this volley. It's a
generational curse.
And Graham's standing there staring at
the guy. And when the guy saw Graham, he
kind of sobered up. He's like, "Hey man,
you know what? Let's just you know,
let's just go our separate ways."
I was like, "All right.
All right then."
That's what I thought then.
Got back in the car.
I said, "Graham,
what were you going to do?
Why'd you come out the car?"
He said, "I was going to see what
happened." I said, "Well, what if he
wanted to fight? Then what would you
do?"
He said, "I was going to kick him."
And he specified where, and it wasn't
the shin bone.
And he was eight. Y'all pray for him.
He said, "I would kick him."
And I said, "Huh." And Elijah was
listening and he goes, "The better
question is, Dad, what were you going to
do?"
Voice of reason, right?
I'm like, "I don't know, son. The Bible
talks about prayer
and the laying on of hands,
and they are both biblical."
I'm misinterpreting the text. See, I do
it, too, okay? Well,
he asked the question, "What are you
going to do then?" He said, "Did you
even think about that if you got in a
fight, we were going to be in the news,
the church was going to be in the news
cuz you got in a fight? And then did you
ever think about that you might go to
jail? And then did you ever think about
that we might grow up without a dad?"
See, cuz he's thinking then,
watch this, all I'm thinking is this.
And it took an 11-year-old for me to be
like,
"Let's go get some Mexican food, boys,
and forget that ever happened."
Don't tell your mom I'll buy you queso.
Just don't don't mention this.
[laughter]
And now I'm telling you as an example,
you see, it's not always going to be
some huge Red Sea moment that you're
responding to.
It's going to be not a Red Sea, but a
parking lot.
Traffic jam.
A bill that comes across.
Something the doctor saw on your lungs
that they weren't planning to see. What
then?
What then?
The knowledge that your marriage is not
really doing so good and now that the
kids are on their way out the house,
maybe you don't really have much to
build on. What then?
And the way I like to picture it for
myself is like this. It's like if we're
telling our story one day and we're
like, you know what?
I went through a horrible time.
>> [clears throat]
>> 2026 or wherever you're watching this in
the future and
I'm going to be honest with you.
I got really disappointed in some people
and I let it fester then I stopped going
to church.
And then after not being in church for a
little while, I like filled the vacuum
with other wrong people in my life and
then
and then it and then it was drinking but
I always I always thought that I could,
you know, I could handle it or or or
then I just, you know, I started
spending so much money as a minute try
to fill the vacuum then I
then I felt so far from God then then
then like put it back up.
How do you want this to end because you
can change?
The end.
You you could say
that was the hardest time in my life.
I got really hurt by some people.
Then
you get to pick the then
that you live next.
>> [applause]
>> I was going to church. I got hurt by
some people but at Elevation it's
amazing cuz they got like 5 million
campuses. So if you want to leave the
church, you can leave the church without
leaving the church. Just go to another
campus and meet some other people.
I'm on another campus then I joined the
greeter team. Did you not see the
testimony today? The lady said, I I felt
like called to volunteer then my husband
volunteered. Then one of my kids got
baptized. Then another one got baptized.
Then another one. Then another one. Then
another one. So which then
Which then? The Bible says, then Moses.
You can change the end. I I can't change
the fact that Pharaoh's chasing me, but
I can stretch what I have and I can take
a forward step. Which then will you tell
when you tell the story one day?
>> [clears throat]
>> Which then
will it be they walked out of my life
and then so I just shut my heart off and
then I never loved again. Then I never
trusted anyone again. And then I never
Then I Then I just gave up. What story
did I want to tell you today?
The church was going good and then they
started criticizing us and it was 2013
and and week after week they kept
talking bad about us. And then I
decided, you know what? Forget y'all. If
y'all don't appreciate my anointing, I'm
out of here. And I walked away from the
church. And that's why I don't even
preach anymore because I can't stand
Christians.
Or do you want to say
and then they told the story of how we
faked our baptisms.
And then I stood up in front of the
church one Sunday morning in 2013 and
said, "Tonight we're going to have a
special baptism service." And then we
baptized 400 people that night. And then
we baptized 1,000 people again the next
year. And then and then and then and
then it could have been the end.
Put it on the board. The end. The end.
The end. It could have been the end.
But then
But then, it could have been the end.
They They could have died right there.
You could die in your disappointment.
Change it. Then you can change the end
[clears throat] with a then. Something
as simple as a then. And if you don't
believe me from the life of Moses,
perhaps we should call on David. David
who was the man after God's own heart.
But in the middle of his life, he
started to become a little bit
distracted by things that he saw and
weary from battles that he had endured.
One day he's walking around his roof and
he sees a woman who's bathing on her
roof. He takes her, which he has the
right to do as a king legally, but it's
wrong to God. In the process of covering
up that sin, he sins again, has her
husband murdered. And the prophet comes
to David and says, "What you did is
wrong. God doesn't like what you did.
God is displeased with WHAT YOU DID. GOD
DOES NOT SEE THIS as your true
potential." And so, the baby is going to
die. David starts fasting. David starts
praying. And it looks like the end, and
it is. The baby does not live. And at
this moment, David has a decision. It is
a hinge decision. The baby did not live.
The consequences happened. His prayer
was not answered. And perhaps that's
where you are in your life TODAY AND WHY
GOD LED ME TO PREACH, YOU CAN change the
end. Because in 2 Samuel 12:20,
the Bible says something very powerful.
Then
David
got up.
>> [laughter]
>> And I see you getting up today.
Because I see you making a decision that
I WILL NOT LET THIS EVENT DEFINE THE
REST OF MY LIFE. I did it. IT WAS WRONG.
I REPENTED. I WEPT. I'm sorry. Create in
me a clean heart, oh God. Then David got
up. Circle the word then, please, so I
can drive THIS HOME. DAVID GOT UP FROM
the ground, washed, put on lotions,
changed his clothes, went to the house
of the Lord, and worshipped. When he
worshipped, then he had the strength to
go to his house. And at his request,
they served him food, and he ate. Verse
24 is even better cuz after he got up
and washed and went to the house and
worshipped and ate, the Bible says
again, "Then David comforted his wife
Bathsheba, and he went to her and made
love to her, and she gave birth to a
son, and they named him Solomon, and the
Lord loved him." And that king went on
to be the greatest, most wise king that
Israel had known. From David's worst
decision, then he got up. Then he went
in. And I came to let you know today,
you don't have to stay stuck in your
regret another day if you don't want to.
My hope is built on nothing less than
Jesus' blood and righteousness.
>> [applause]
>> Then,
David
got up.
Make eye contact with your neighbor.
Say, "Get up."
Get up. Repent and get up. Wash your
face and get up. Change your shirt and
get up. Say you're sorry and move
forward.
Then,
or perhaps if you don't believe David,
you'll believe Samson.
Maybe if you don't believe me and you
don't believe Moses and you don't
believe David
and you feel like this is the end for
me, maybe you'll believe Samson
who got the most expensive haircut in
the history of humanity. Talk about a
hinge decision.
A haircut turned into his eyes being
gouged out and the loss of his strength
because of the breaking of his vow. And
Samson, with his eyes gouged out, is
standing in the column as they worship
Dagon, the false god, and they're
mocking him. And perhaps you feel like
that right now. Like, man, I just feel
so embarrassed. I feel so humiliated.
And Samson, at his lowest moment, you
listening to me? I'm telling you you can
change the end. The Bible says in Judges
16:28, "Then
Samson prayed to the Lord." Pray about
it, baby. It's not over. He prayed to
the Lord, "Sovereign Lord, remember me.
Please, God, strengthen me just once
more and let me with one blow get
revenge on the Philistines for my two
eyes."
And then Samson reached
You missed it, Justin.
Then Samson reached I'm telling you that
you get to pick your next then. You get
to pick your next then. You don't get to
control the result, but you control your
response. You get to pick your next
then.
The result belongs to God, the response
belongs to you.
And Samson mocked, can't see, blind,
humiliated, defeated, disgraced,
embarrassed. Then Samson reached toward
the two central pillars on which the
temple stood, bracing himself against
them, his right hand on the one, put it
on the screen, the end, and his left
hand on the other. The Bible says,
change it. Watch this. Samson said, let
me die with the Philistines. Then he
pushed with all HIS MIGHT AND DOWN CAME
THE TEMPLE OF THE FALSE GOD AND DOWN
CAME THE VERDICT over his life that it
was over. And down came the temple and
thus he killed more
when he died than when he lived.
It's not too late for you. Then, then,
then, what then shall [clears throat]
you say?
Then I gave up
or then I stepped up.
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> Then I stayed down
or then I got up.
And maybe if you don't believe me or
Moses, David, or Samson,
maybe you believe Peter.
Peter denied he even knew the Lord. He
sat down by the fire and acted like he
wasn't even a follower of his
best friend.
You can feel like you disappointed God
sometimes so bad that you'll never get
up.
But I thank God for the day of
Pentecost.
I said, I thank God for Acts chapter 2.
>> [applause]
>> I thank God for Romans 8:31. What then?
Cuz Acts 2:14 says, then
Peter stood UP. EVERYBODY STAND UP ON
your feet right now. THIS IS YOUR part
in the message.
Hit your neighbor, say, stand up, God's
not done with you. Get up, it's not
over. GET UP, IT'S NOT [music] GONE. GET
UP, IT'S NOT LOST. AND PETER PREACHED SO
GOOD THAT 3,000 PEOPLE GOT [music] SAVED
CUZ HE STOOD UP.
>> [music]
>> Maybe if you don't believe Peter,
you'll believe the thief
who was hanging on a cross.
He didn't do anything right to deserve
to be saved.
His friend was mocking Jesus, but he had
a little bit of faith.
Just a little bit of faith. Not enough
to get his ACT TOGETHER. HE DIDN'T even
have long left. For all of you who THINK
THAT THERE'S NOT ENOUGH TIME, YOU CAN
CHANGE to the end.
Because the Bible says that while one
hurled insults, and one said, "Save us
if you're really who you say you are."
There was one thief on the cross, and
there was one then that he spoke. And
this is the message. Then he said,
"JESUS." WHEN YOU SAY JESUS, I DON'T
CARE WHAT YOU'VE BEEN THROUGH. WHEN YOU
SAY JESUS, when you CALL ON THE NAME,
COME ON SOMEBODY. HELP me preach this.
WHEN YOU SAY JESUS, demons flee. When
you say Jesus, waters part. When you say
Jesus, [music]
>> [applause]
>> he said, "JESUS,
REMEMBER ME WHEN you come in your
kingdom."
And Jesus looked back and said, "Because
you said then, I say to you, truly I
tell you today,
you will be with me in paradise. And the
Egyptians you see today, you will see no
more
because of this then."
Now the word of the Lord has come with
power and velocity and great personal
application to you today. What will you
do with this word? You are responsible
for it.
That in real time,
the familiar sounds of Pharaoh behind
you, that's the old life. The unfamiliar
terrain of the life of faith that awaits
you, this is a hinge
moment.
What
then
shall you say?
You know, I spent years away from God.
Then one day I
I went to church.
And the preacher was preaching and it
got to this moment
and I realized I need God.
I need God.
>> [music and applause]
>> And I And I And I lifted my hands to
him.
And I begin to worship him.
And I begin to praise him and I said,
"God, I'm
I'm sorry for what I did. I repent of my
sins. But God, can you raise me up?"
And because of that then
it changed [music] the end. And that's
why I'm here today.
That's why I'm lifting both of my hands.
>> [music]
>> Play God, I'm just grateful. That's why
I'm lifting both of my hands.
Cuz he gave me chance
after chance
after [music] chance.
Come on, THIS IS NOT THE END.
THIS IS NOT THE END.
GET UP LIKE [music] DAVID and worship.
Brace yourself like Samson and push.
>> [music]
>> LIKE PETER, STAND UP AND PREACH.
LIKE THE PEOPLE ON THE CROSS, say Jesus.
>> [music]
>> Jesus.
Jesus.
Yeah.
>> [music]
>> Hey, thank you for watching the
Elevation Church YouTube. I want you to
subscribe. That way you can know when we
go live and post new [music] content.
Make sure leave me a comment. Let me
know what spoke to you today, where
you're watching [music] from, and what
we can pray for you about. And if you'd
like to support the ministry
financially,
>> [music]
>> you can click the give button now and
help us continue reaching people around
the world for Jesus [music] Christ.
Thanks again. I'll see you next time.